Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Series XIV. Subject Files, 1922-2008
  - Rothenstein, John (Tate Gallery, London - Director), 1946, 2006-2008 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Russell, Sean, Sep 13, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Ryan, Desmond (author), 1984-2003 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Sheehan, Eugene (Gene), 1983 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Sheehy, Michael, 1940-1952, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Christy and Anne, 1959, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Somerville-Large, Sammy, 1950, 2004 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Stewart, Dorothy, circa 1956 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Strand, Paul I, 1921-2008 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Strand, Paul II, 1921-2008 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Stuart, Francis, 1983-2000 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson and Laura I, 1945-2008 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson and Laura II, 1945-2008 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Sykes, Gerald, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - Tobin, Marion, 1986-2005, undated (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - Truden, Bernardine, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - University College Cork Archives (Catriona Mulcahy), 2005 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - University College Dublin Archives, circa 2003 (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Varney, John (New York University), 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Villard, Marquita, 1933-2007 (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Wall, Mervyn (Radio Eireann), 1972-1984 (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - Walsh, Frank P., 1929 (Box 27, Folder 25)
  - Walsh, Roisin (Chief Librarian, City of London Public Library); family, 1930s, 2004 (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Walston, Catherine and Henry, 1935-2007 (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Weston, Edward, 1969-2003, undated (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - White, James, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - Whittlesey, Eunice Stoddard Smith (Mrs. Julian H.), 1983-2004 (Box 27, Folder 30)
  - Yaddo Foundation I, 1955, 1983-1999 (Box 27, Folder 31)
  - Yaddo Foundation II, 1955, 1983-1999 (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Yeats, Jack B. (lists, notes), undated (Box 27, Folder 33)
  - Young, Ella, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 34)
  - Trinity College - Microfilm of Childers Correspondence, Manuscript Department; Manuscript: 7850/885-911 (copies available in Series under Childers), undated (Box 29)
  - Interviews: 3 reel tapes. 2. EOM, Conn Ranger; 4: Comer, Jack and Madge; 5. Thomas and Peggy Malone (Sean Ford), Madge Clifford Comer, Jack Comer., 1970 (Box 29)
- Series XV. Printed Ephemera, 1789-1950
  Items in this series reflect O'Malley's varied interests in Irish history, cartography, art and many other areas and include prints, reprints, maps, photographs, essays, brochures, letters, drawings, reproductions and other ephemeral materials and artifacts collected or inherited by Ernie O'Malley. While most of the graphic items in this series are reprints or reproductions, several original cards, drawings and paintings from notable artists including Roy Boynton, and Jack Hanlon are also included. Nearly twenty maps and nine letters either written by or addressed to historically significant Irishmen and women including Eva Gore Booth, Standish O' Grady, Sean O'Sullivan and Thomas Grattan complete the series as well as an undated historic account of the Spanish Armada's landing and an indenture for land dated 1857.
  The items are arranged in alphabetical order with original inventory numbers included on the folders.
  - Printed Ephemera Index, 2010 (Box 27, Folder 35)
  - Account: "Spanish Fleet Landing in Kinsdale, Ireland in 1601" handwritten, [John Blake Dillon?], undated (Box 27, Folder 36)
  - Applegood, Frank G.: "Domingo" photocopy of engraving; Taos, NM, pre 1932 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - The Blasket Island from Don Quin (print of woodcut), undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Christmas card by Jack Hanlon, signed by artist, circa 1945 (Box 27, Folder 40)
  - Christmas card signed by Jack B. Yeats (photocopy), circa 1948-1949 (Box 27, Folder 41)
  - Christmas card; signed "to Ernie from Katherine", circa 1933 (Box 27, Folder 42)
  - Clare, Austin: pencil drawing, reproduction, 1924 (Box 27, Folder 43)
  - County Cork: essay, manuscript on, undated (Box 27, Folder 47)
  - DeValera, Eamon: print of portrait, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - DeValera, Eamon "Taioseach's Broadcast to the Nation" delivered May 16, 1945; reprint from the Irish Press, May 17, 1945 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Early Irish History and Kingship: essay, manuscript on, undated (Box 27, Folder 48)
  - Frost, Stella: Landscape (photoprint), circa 1947 (Box 27, Folder 72)
  - Gore, Booth, Eva: Correspondence to Seamus O'Sullivan, undated (Box 27, Folder 49)
  - Gore, Booth, Eva: Correspondence to W. Russell, undated (Box 27, Folder 50)
  - Grattan, Henry: letter, Apr 5, 1789 (Box 27, Folder 51)
  - The Gypsy (publication) cover woodcut by Allan Cole, 1916 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Harvard Univeristy official register: Courses and Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1928-1929 (Box 27, Folder 69)
  - Horgan, Paul: "Cathedral Altar" reprints, woodcut, circa 1945-1950 (Box 27, Folder 74)
  - "The Hurricane" poem by Hart Crane on his personal stationery) typescript, Jan 1931 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Indenture (vellum) "Conveyance of a piece of land" in Charlott St, Leister, England; Rev. William Tiptaft to Willaim Tomblin Keal, Esq., 1857 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Jones, Colonel Edward: essay on, late 1800s (Box 27, Folder 46)
  - Lawrence, D.H. photocopy of [wood]print of head, circa 1950s (Box 27, Folder 75)
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge: drawing of home in Taos, NM "Los Gallos", circa 1929 (Box 27, Folder 45)
  - Mahony, Francis: Correspondence to Crofton Coker, Oct 31, 1841 (Box 27, Folder 52)
  - Manuscript: MacDareo's "Noshel" (Fermoy and Ballymole Books), circa late 1800s, undated (Box 27, Folder 37)
  - Map: "A Plan and a section of the River Nore from City of Kilkenny to the town of Enniscorthy with elevations of Kilkenny canal", circa late 1800s (Box 27, Folder 67)
  - Map: Ancient Map of Irish Districts in Queen's County and County Kildare (reprint), undated (Box 27, Folder 58)
  - Map: Avignon, France, undated (Box 27, Folder 59)
  - Map: Cambridge, Great Britain (signed by Ernie O'Malley), circa 1945-1955 (Box 27, Folder 60)
  - Map: "The Cittie of Limerick from Thomas Pacata's "Pacata Hibernia"" or "A History of the Wars in Ireland during the Reign of Queen Elizabeth (color engraving), 1820 reprint, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Map: Diocese of Tuam, undated (Box 27, Folder 68)
  - Map: France: Michelin Guide Northern France, undated (Box 27, Folder 61)
  - Map: France, Northwestern (annotated by Ernie O'Malley), undated (Box 27, Folder 66)
  - Map: "Galway the Capital of Connaught in the Kingdom of Ireland, 1651" drawn and engraved, 1820 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Map: Great Western Railway of England: Handbook for Travellers from Overseas, undated (Box 27, Folder 62)
  - Map: Indian and Ceylon, undated (Box 27, Folder 63)
  - Map: Kilkenny; showing seats of original septs and ancient tribe lands, undated (Box 27, Folder 64)
  - Map: La Cote D'Azur (France), circa 1938 (Box 27, Folder 65)
  - Map: "Map of the City of Dublin and Township of Rathmines", 1864 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Map: "Map of Ireland engraved for the Loyal National Repead Association", circa 1840s (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Map: Mayo, Sheet 67 [Northside of Clew Bay], published by Director General at the Ordinance Survey Office, Phoenix Park, Dublin 1920 [*Covers O'Malley's home at Burrishoole Lodge, near Clew Bay], undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Map: "Pictorial Map of Mexico" by Miguel Gomex Median (color reproduction) published by Fischgrund Publishng Co., Mexico (exclusive publishers of Diego River's Frescoes), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Map: Youghal as in Elizabeth's reign when sacked by the insurgent Earl of Desmond (reprint), undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Mitchel, John: Correspondence to Charles Magee, Dec 24, 1845 (Box 27, Folder 53)
  - Nepsil House Flats brochure (where Ernie O'Malley rented a flat, 1954-1957), circa 1954 (Box 27, Folder 38)
  - O'Grady, Standish: Correspondence to Miss Costello, undated (Box 27, Folder 54)
  - O'Grady, Standish: Correspondence to Mr. Law, undated (Box 27, Folder 55)
  - O'Malley, Ernie: Wallet (used while in New Mexico), 1931 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - O'Sullivan, Sean: prints and various protraits by, 1929-1939 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - O'Sullivan, Sean print: Portrait of Douglas Hyde, reprinted by The Irish Press, Christmas, 1938 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlet: What is Happening in France by Isabel Brown. published by the Anti-Fascist Relief Committee, London, cundated (Box 27, Folder 71)
  - The Path of the Hangman (illustration); verso poem "Where is the Flag of England?", 1916 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Postcards: Spain, Bruges, Le Port du Cehval, undated (Box 27, Folder 73)
  - Preface cover of publication; woodcut by Allan Cole, undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Print: "Der Seestrum" [The Storm] unknown artist; printed by A. Felgner, Berlin, Lith v. Buscheck, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Print: "Grand Entry of the Sovereigns into Paris" on the 31 March 1814 by R. Boywer (color engraving) 1 Pall Mall [London], 1816 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Print: "Inside View of the Royal Stock Exchange at London," Thomas Bowles, color engraving, circa mid-18th century, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Print: Untitled [study of female nude], charcoal drawing, reprinted in conte color from 1812 original, undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Print in color: Wofle Tone by New Ireland Assurance Company, printed at the Signg of the Three Candles, Dublin, circa 1935-1945 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Prints: (items 16-72 through 16-78: Untitled [Four Courts Dublin], 16-77: The Four Law Courts, Dublin; 16-78: The Law Courts [Four Courts Dublin] late 18th century, undated (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - [Sketch of Dress Designs] Plates SVI, "No. 19 - Cantilly, Musee Conde" by unknown, circa 1930-1940 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Songs from the Four Winds of Eirinn by Ethna Carberry signed and dated by Ernie O'Malley, 1919 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Stationery: Card, Cuala Press, circa 1940s (Box 27, Folder 44)
  - Stationery: Card with reproduction of a Paul Henry painting circa 1940s (blank inside), undated (Box 27, Folder 39)
  - "View of Proach Patrick" by Augustus John (reprint in publication), undated (Box 27, Folder 70)
  - Walker, Charles: Correspondence to Mr. Starkey, Jan 29, 1907 (Box 27, Folder 57)
  - Yeats, William Butler: Correspondence to Mr. MacCartan (photocopy) Jun 14, 19__, undated (Box 27, Folder 56)
  - Yeats, William Butler, photoprint of portrait by Sean O'Sullivan, circa 1920 (Box 28, Folder 7)